Guide to the Thomas Merton papers,
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Thomas Merton Papers,
1923-1989
Merton, Thomas, 1915-1968.
20 linear ft. (ca. 10,250 items in 40 boxes)
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
4079099
Biographical Note
Thomas Merton (Father Louis), M.A. Columbia 1939, was a widely read Catholic author and social critic who lived as a member of the Cistercian Order of the Strict Observance, the Trappists, from 1941 till his death in Bangkok in 1968.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, manuscripts, documents, photographs, art work, audio cassette, printed materials by and about Thomas Merton. The correspondence covers the years from his study at Columbia to his death in Bangkok. Among the cataloged correspondence are: Daniel Berrigan, Mark Van Doren, Luis Somoza, Jacque Maritain, Aldous Huxley, James Laughlin, Robert Lax, Grover Cleveland Smith, John Howard Griffin, William Henry Shannon and Victoria Ocampo. The extensive manuscript collection was assembled primarily by Sister Thérèse Lentfoehr, Mark Van Doren, and Robert Shepherd. Among the more significant manuscripts are: corrected typescript of THE SEVEN STOREY MOUNTAIN; fragments of his NOVITIATE JOURNAL; notebooks and journals used in THE SIGN OF JONAS; numerous draft of poems; most of his lecture and conference notes which he used while serving as master of scholastics and, later, master of novices. There is an extensive collection of mimeographed articles, many inscribed to Sister Thérèse Lentfoehr; four watercolors by his father, Owen Merton, and many humorous and devotional drawings by Merton; many photographs of Merton, as well as photographs taken by Merton. There is an audio cassette of the radio play by Bruce Stewart entitled ME AND MY SHADOW, produced by the BBC in 1989. The printed material consists of numerous clippings and some offprints, pamphlets, and books.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into 3 series:
Series I: Cataloged Material
Series II: Arranged Material
Series III: Printed Material
Subjects
Berrigan, Daniel.; Merton, Owen, 1887-1931.; Laughlin, James, 1914-1997.; Griffin, John Howard, 1920-1980.; Maritain, Jacques, 1882-1973.; Rice, Edward.; Ocampo, Victoria, 1890-1979.; Lax, Robert.; Smith, Grover Cleveland, 1923-; Pennington, M. Basil.; Van Doren, Mark, 1894-1972.; Waugh, Evelyn, 1903-1966.; Somoza Debayle, Luis, 1922-1967.; Mason, Herbert, 1932-; American literature--20th century.; Authors, American--20th century.; Religious poetry.; Religious literature.; Catholics.; Catholic authors--20th century.; Monks.; Poets, American--20th century.; Photoprints.; Audio cassettes; Drawings.; Paintings.; Poems.; Clergy.
Access Restrictions
This collection has no restrictions.
This collection is located on-site.
Acquisition
1964 M-64 Merton, Thomas Gift
07/01/88 M-88-07-01 10,200 items Merton Center Purchase
Gift of Thomas Merton, 1964.
Purchase, 1982, 1988.
- Series I: Cataloged Material
  - Subseries I.1: Correspondence
    - Berrigan, Daniel (Box 1)
    - Griffin, John Howard, 1920-1980 (Box 1)
    - Huxley, Aldous (Box 1)
    - Laughlin, James (Box 1)
    - Lax, Robert (Box 1)
    - McDonell, Tom (Box 1)
    - Maritain, Jacques, 1882-1973 (Box 1)
    - Merton, Thomas (Box 1-3)
    - Ocampo, Victoria, 1891- (Box 3)
    - Rice, Edward E.1918- (Box 3)
    - Shannon, William H. (Box 3)
    - Smith, Grover Cleveland, 1923- (Box 3)
    - Somoza, Luis A. (Box 3)
    - Van Doren, Mark (Box 3)
    - Waugh, Evelyn, 1903-1966 (Box 3)
  - Subseries I.2: Manuscripts
    - Berrigan, Daniel (Box 4)
    - Cortes, Alfonso (Box 4)
    - Lax, Robert (Box 4)
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese (Box 4)
    - MA Political Action for Peace (Box 4)
    - Merton, Thomas (Box 4-19)
    - Pennington, Basil (Box 19)
    - Pessoa, Fernando (Box 19)
  - Subseries I.3: Documents
    - Artists and Writers for Hughes (Box 19)
  - Subseries I.4: Photographs
    - Berrigan, Daniel (Box 20)
    - Dalai Lama (Box 20)
    - Griffin, John Howard (Box 20)
    - Lax, Robert (Box 20)
    - Maritain, Jacques (Box 20)
    - Merton, Thomas (Box 20)
    - Rice, Edward E. (Box 20)
    - Sheen, Fulton John, 1895- (Box 20)
    - Van Doren, Mark (Box 20)
    - Walsh, Daniel (Box 20)
  - Subseries I.5: Art
    - Antonucci, Emil (Box 13/8/6)
    - Hammer, Victor Photograph of his portrait of Merton (Box 13/8/6)
    - Merton, Owen Art, (4 oversize watercolors ) (Box 13/8/6)
      [Three shelved in the Map Case, the fourth is hanging in the Vault ]
  - Subseries I.6: Audio-Visual
    - Gray, Richard The Poems of Thomas Merton Read by Richard Grey, New York: Spirit Records, [n.d.], (1record album ) (Box 13/8/6)
    - Stewart, Bruce Me and My Shadow, [Bristol], 1989, (1 Audio cassette ) (Box 20)
      [Radio play on the life of Thomas Merton; accompanying t.l.s. from John Stanley]
- Series II: Arranged Material
  - Subseries II.1: Correspondence
    - Merton, Thomas Letters to Lax, Gibney and other close friends, ca.1941, (Carbon copies ) (Box 21)
      [Unsigned and arranged A-Z.]
    - Merton, Thomas Letters to various people, (2 folders (Carbon copies, photocopies, etc.) ) (Box 21)
    - Merton, Thomas Mimeographed circular letters: "Advent-Christmas letters," "Asian Letters", [v.p.], 1967-1968, (2 folders ) (Box 21)
    - McInerny, Dennis Letter to Brother Patrick Hart, [v.p.], [v.d.] (Box 21)
    - Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr American Broadcasting Company (Box 21)
    - Bamberger, Abbot John Etudes Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr Bellarmine College (Box 21)
    - Bernice Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Berns, Dorothy A. Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Biering, René Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - The Cashions Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Father Christopher Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Dinter, Father Paul Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Doubleday & Co. Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Durback, Robert Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Flood, Brother Maurice Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Ford, John J. Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Forest, Jim Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Fox, Dom James Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Gnass, George, S.J. Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Father Gerard, O.C.S.O. Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Hart, Brother Patrick Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr, (14 folders ) (Box 21)
    - Horvath, Adam Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Jeffs, Joseph E. Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Jellema, Rod Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Lax, Robert Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - McQuilkin, Frank Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Father Magsam Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Maloney, Stephen R. Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Martin, Father M. Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr New Directions (Box 21)
    - O'Callaghan, Tommie Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - O'Neil, Harry Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Pick, Dr. John Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Father Roseliep Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Schusky, Mary Sue Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Seitz, Ron Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Stark, Philip, S.J. Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr (Box 21)
    - Stone, Naomi Burton Letters to Sister Therese Lentfoehr, (3 folders ) (Box 21)
      [With 1 t.l.s. from Sister Therese.]
    - Andrade, Jaime Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Andrade, Jorge Carrera Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Arrés, Therese Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Boutoute, Abbé Louis Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Cavero, Carlos Duelo Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Letters to Thomas Merton Conferencia Episcopal Argentina (Box 22)
    - Letters to Thomas Merton Curtis Brown, Ltd. (Box 22)
    - de Hueck, Catherine Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Dell'Isola, Frank Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Letters to Thomas Merton Editorial Sur S.A. (Box 22)
    - Sister Emmanuel Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Gibney, Bob Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Keegan, Daniel José Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Libra, Clara Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Maritain, Jacques Letters to Thomas Merton, (Photocopies ) (Box 22)
    - Moutini, J. B. Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Phillipe, Monsignor Paul Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Pick, Dr. John Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Reinhardt, Ad Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Ricuarte, Jose Euselio Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Rueda G., Marco V. Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Salazar, Juilo Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Unidentified Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Vigolle, Germaine Letters to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Laughlin, Brother Patrick Hart, Dan Walsh, et al. Letters relating to Thomas Merton (Box 22)
    - Telegrams (2) re Merton's death Circular letter from Gethsemani Homily at the mass for Father M Louis (Box 22)
    - Circular lettersFriends of Gethsemani (Box 22)
    - Envelopes, (3 folders ) (Box 22)
  - Subseries II.2: Manuscripts
    - Butterworth, Mrs. O. L. "Gnothi Seauton", (Poem ) (Box 23)
    - Caputi, Ilaria "Il Primo Thomas Merton: The Seven Storey Mountain", (1v. Ph.D. dissertation. ) (Box 23)
    - Giroux, Robert. Notes on the manuscript of "The Seven Storey Mountain" (Box 23)
    - Kramer, Victor "Thomas Merton Oral History", (1 Bound volume ) (Box 23)
      [in Box 35 of the collection]
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese Classification of some of Merton's poems (Box 23)
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese Extracts of Merton poems (Box 23)
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese "Merton and Education" (Box 23)
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese Miscellaneous manuscript material (Box 23)
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese Notes on Evelyn Waugh letters to Merton (Box 23)
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese Notes on Merton's life and works for talks, (3 folders ) (Box 23)
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese "A Response to Thomas Merton: The Dimensions of Solitude" (Box 23)
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese "Thomas Merton: Poet in his Time" (Box 23)
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese Transcription of Merton's letter to Time re James Joyce (Box 23)
    - Merton, Thomas Curriculum Vitae (Box 23)
  - Subseries II.3: Lectures and Conferences
    - Ascetical and Mystical Theology, Gethsemani, KY, 1961, (1 volume Mimeograph ) (Box 24)
    - Background and Attitude of Monastic Postulants, in Relation to the Failure of Vocation, Gethsemani, KY, [n.d.], (12 page Typeseript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
    - Conferences: Two lists of the material sent by Merton to Sister Therese, as well a a signed note by Merton ragarding the material, dated Nov. 14 [1958] (Box 24)
    - Conferences: Two envelopes which contained the material sent to Sister Therese by Merton in November of 1958. One inscribed "The Mystery of Mary and the Church -- Conference" and the other "Conference - Liturgical Feasts and Seasons". (Box 24)
      [Contents removed and re-foldered. See the follwing records for a detailed description of this material.]
    - "All Saints", (5 page Typescript (carbon, with ms. correction) ) (Box 24)
      [Sent by Merton to Sister Therese Lentfoehr 11/10/1958]
    - "The Angels", (4 page Typescript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
    - "The Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary", (2 page Typescript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
    - “The Assumption of the Blessed Virgin Mary”, (1 page Typescript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
      [Sent by Merton to Sister Therese Lentfoehr, 11/3/1958]
    - “The Assumption of Our Lady in the Byzantine Rite”, (1 page Typescript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
    - “Candlemas”, (3 page Typescript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
    - “Conference on Prayer”, (6 page Typescript (mimeograph, with ms corrections) ) (Box 24)
    - “Exaltation of the Holy Cross”, (1 page Holograph ) (Box 24)
      [Sent by Merton to Sister Therese Lentfoehr, 11/10/1958]
    - “Feast of all the Saints of the Order”, (2 page Typescript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
    - “Feast of the Dedication of the Church”, (5 page Typescript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
    - “Feast of the Holy Name of Mary”, (1 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Feast of the Immaculate Heart of Mary", (1 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Feast of the Nativity of Our Lady", (2 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Feast of Our Holy Father St Benedict", (2 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Feast of Our Lady’s Presentation", (4 page Typescript (with ms. correction) ) (Box 24)
    - "Feast of Saint Anne", (2 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Feast of the St Joseph", (3 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Feast of Saint Luke II", (1 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Feast of the Seven Dolors", (3 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Feast of the Transfiguration", (1 page Typescript (with ms. correction) ) (Box 24)
    - "Feast of the Visitation", (1 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Holy Rosary II", (1 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "May – Consecration to Our Lady", (1 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Mary in the Passions", (1 page Typescript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
    - "Monroe Conference on Contemplative Living", (13 page Mimeograph ) (Box 24)
      [With cover letter
      Sent by Merton to Sister Therese Lentfoehr, 11/3-/1958]
    - "The Mystery of Mary and the Church", (3 page Typescript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
    - "Nativity of Our Lady II", (2 page Typescript (with ms. corrections) ) (Box 24)
    - "The Nativity of Saint John the Baptist", (4 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Office of the Feast of Saint Bernard", (3 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Pax Huic Domui: Monastic Peace", (3 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "The Priest in the Monastery – Feast of Saint Thomas the Apostle", (3 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "The Reception of the Holy Crown of Thorns", (1 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "The Rosary and Its Mysteries", (6 page Typescript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
    - "Saint Alfred – Cistercian Life on His Time", (2 page Typescript (with ms. correction) ) (Box 24)
    - "Saint Bernard’s Sermons for the Feast of Saint Andrew", (4 page Typescript (carbon, with ms. corrections) ) (Box 24)
    - "Saint Lawrence", (1 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Saint Martin", (2 page Typescript (carbon) ) (Box 24)
    - "Saint Mary Magdalen", (3 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Saint Robert and the Foundation of Citeaux", (3 page Typescript (with ms. addition) ) (Box 24)
    - "Saint Stephen Harding", (3 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Saint Stephen Harding (Comm Of Confessors)", (1 page Typescript ) (Box 24)
    - "Saints Peter and Paul", (1 page Typescript (with ms. addition) ) (Box 24)
    - "Saints Simon and Jude", (4 page Holograph ) (Box 24)
    - "Scripture and the Cistercian", (1 page Mimeograph ) (Box 24)
    - Gallo Roman Monasticism/Cassian/The Regula Magistri/and the Background to the Rule of Saint Benedict, Trappist, KY, 1963, (96 page Mimeograph ) (Box 24)
    - An Introduction to Cistercian Theology, Trappist, KY, 1950-1952, (2 volumes Mimeograph ) (Box 24)
    - An Introduction to Cistercian Theology, Trappist, KY, 1950-1952, (71 pages Typescript (with ms. corrections) ) (Box 24)
    - Liturgical Feasts and Seasons (Box 25)
    - Monastic Fathers (Box 25)
    - Monastic Orientation (Box 25)
    - Monastic Orientation Series III - V (Box 26)
    - Monastic Orientation Series V (cont) - VI (Box 27)
    - Pre-Benedictine Monachism (Box 27)
    - A Program of Studies: The virtues of the common life as helps to the religious life (Box 27)
    - The Spiritual Doctrine of St Ammonas (Box 27)
    - Miscellaneous: Poems, (3 folders ) (Box 28)
      [Photocopies, mimeographed, etc., A-Z.]
    - Merton, Thomas Reviews by Merton (Box 28)
    - Merton Center (Box 28)
    - Miscellaneous material relating to Merton (Box 28)
    - Miscellaneous manuscript material (Box 28)
    - Lawlor, Patrick Thomas Merton: The Poet and the Contemplative Life, (1v. Manuiscript of catalog, galleys, page proofs, etc. ) (Box 28)
  - Subseries II.4: Documents
    - Merton, Thomas Last will and testament, (Photocopy. ) (Box 28)
    - AgreementMerton Legacy Trust (Box 28)
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese Catalog information for the material in her Thomas Merton collection and the original folders used by her to secure the manuscript of "The Seven Storey Mountain" (Box 29)
    - Card catalogue (incomplete) of its holdings Merton Center (Box 30)
  - Subseries II.5: Photographs
    - Merton, Thomas Framed photograph & matted photograph of Merton (Box 13/8/6)
    - Thomas Merton Childhood and family (Box 31)
    - Thomas Merton at Columbia University (Box 31)
    - Ordination, first mass, etc (Box 31)
    - Bangkok conference (Box 31)
    - Funeral mass (Box 31)
    - Grave (Box 31)
    - Bust (Box 31)
    - Greenwich Village apartment (Box 31)
    - Monastery of Gethsemani (Box 31)
    - Hermitage (Box 31)
    - Funeral mass in Bangkok (Box 31)
    - Hart, Brother Patrick et al. (Box 31)
    - Walsh, Daniel (Box 31)
    - Zilboorg, Gregory (Box 31)
    - Chairs, room, etc (Box 31)
    - Desert rocks, New Mexico (Box 31)
    - Houses (Box 31)
    - School House, Pleasant Hill (Box 31)
    - Shrine of St Therese (Box 31)
    - Sister Therese Lentfoehr At Merton exhibit (Box 31)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 31)
    - Merton, Thomas Photographs by Thomas Merton (Box 31)
  - Subseries II.6: Art
    - Manessier, Alfred. "Crown of Thorns", (1 Photograph ) (Box 32)
    - Merton, Thomas Calligraphies: Series of six (Box 32)
      [1 of the 6 retained by William H. Shannon]
    - Merton, Thomas Calligraphies Series of four (Box 32)
      [3 of the 4 retained by William H. Shannon]
    - Series of eight: "La Vida Politica" Calligraphies, (8 folders ) (Box 32)
      [1 retained by William H. Shannon]
    - Lentfoehr, Sister Therese Drawings by Sister Therese (Box 32)
    - Merton, Thomas Drawing of a Cross (Box 32)
      [Shelved in mapcase 13/8/6]
    - Merton, Thomas Drawings of Figures, (45 folders ) (Box 32)
    - Merton, Thomas Calligraphic drawings of figures, (5 folders ) (Box 32)
    - Merton, Thomas Drawing of a guitar (Box 32)
    - Merton, Thomas Drawings of Heads, (30 folders ) (Box 32)
    - Merton, Thomas Feast Day Card (Box 32)
    - Merton, Thomas Watercolor: "A Pastoral" (Box 32)
    - Shannon, William H. Calligraph (Box 32)
    - Sissons, Grace Pencil and crayon drawing (Box 32)
- Series III: Printed Material
  - Subseries III.1: General
    - Beecher, John. "On Acquiring a Cistercian Breviary" [Poem] (Box 33)
  - Subseries III.2: Clippings
    - Archibald MscLeish & Lewis Mumford (Box 33)
    - Art Exhibit (Box 33)
    - Gethsemani and other monasteries (Box 33)
    - Father Irenaeus Herscher & St Bonaventure (Box 33)
    - Merton (Box 33)
    - Merton's death (Box 33)
  - Subseries III.3: Reviews
    - Ascent to Truth (Box 33)
    - Asian Journal (Box 33)
    - Bread in the Wilderness (Box 33)
    - Clement of Alexandria (Box 33)
    - Collected Poems (Box 33)
    - Conjectures of a Guilty Bystander (Box 33)
    - Contemplation on a World of Action (Box 33)
    - Disputed Questions (Box 33)
    - Elected Silence (Box 33)
    - Figures for an Apocalypse (Box 33)
    - A Hidden Wholeness (Box 33)
    - Life and Holiness (Box 33)
    - The Living Bread (Box 33)
    - Love and Living (Box 33)
    - My Argument with the Gestapo (Box 33)
    - Mystics and Zen Masters (Box 33)
    - The New Man (Box 33)
    - No Man is an Island (Box 33)
    - Secular Journal (Box 33)
    - Seeds of Contemplation (Box 33)
    - Seeds of Destruction (Box 33)
    - The Seven Storey Mountain (Box 33)
    - Sign of Jonas (Box 33)
    - The Strange Islands (Box 33)
    - Tears of the Blind Lions (Box 33)
    - Thomas Merton, Monk (Box 33)
    - Thomas Merton on Peace (Box 33)
    - Thomas Merton Reader (Box 33)
    - Waters of Silence (Box 33)
    - Waters of Siloe (Box 33)
    - What Are These Wounds? (Box 33)
    - Zen and the Birds of Appetite (Box 33)
  - Subseries III.4: Articles, Poems, etc.
    - The Shakers (Box 33)
    - Ed Rice (Box 33)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 33)
    - Lax, Robert "A Poem for Thomas Merton" (Box 33)
    - Merton, Thomas Articles and essays, (3 folders ) (Box 34)
    - Merton, Thomas "Five Drawings by Thomas Merton" (Box 34)
    - Merton, Thomas "Four Freedom Songs" (Box 34)
    - Merton, Thomas Poems (Box 34)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 34)
  - Subseries III.5: Offprints
    - The Christmas Sermons of Bl Guerric (Box 35)
    - The Climate of Monastic Prayer (Box 35)
    - Conversatio Morum (Box 35)
    - Examination of Conscience (Box 35)
    - For a Renewal of Eremitism in the Monastic State (Box 35)
    - Liturgical Renewal (Box 35)
    - The Pasternak Affair in Perspective (Box 35)
    - La vida solitaria (Box 35)
    - The Zen Koa (Box 35)
  - Subseries III.6: Offprints and Articles re. Merton
    - Pamphlets: Miscellaneous, (2 folders ) (Box 35)
    - Pamphlets: The Monk in the Diaspora (Box 35)
    - Pamphlets: Thomas Merton Books, Fall 1988, (Catalog ) (Box 35)
    - Pamphlets: Two Articles by Thomas Merton (Box 35)
    - Columbia Yearbook, 1937, (Tearsheets ) (Box 35)
    - "The Jester", (Tearsheets ) (Box 35)
    - Vespers Funeral Mass & Burial Mass for Thomas Merton (Box 35)
  - Subseries III.7: Books and Oral History
    - Books by Merton and others (Box 36)
    - Victor Kramer's "Thomas Merton Oral History" (Box 36)
    - Translations of books by Thomas Merton (Box 37-40)